Hi, I'm Sandra, from HEARa.
Welcome to Day 5 of our
10-day Lip reading Challenge,
designed to help you develop and
practice your lip reading skills!
Hearing loss can have a profound impact on your life.
It touches every interaction.
It can affect your career, your relationships,
and your happiness.
Join me to explore tips and
tricks on this YouTube channel
to bring confidence and clarity
to relationships in all areas of your life.
Today is all about vowels.
Vowels are useful to learn for two reasons:
the first is that there's a
vowel in every word in English,
so if we learn more about them,
we can increase our speech reading
skills exponentially!
The second reason is that
it's mostly the vowels
that give rise to accents.
For example,
American English and British English
have all the same consonants.
It's the vowel sounds
that make them sound different.
Many people with hearing loss
have difficulty with accents.
There is a key difference
between vowels and consonants
when it comes to lip reading.
A rule to remember is that the mouth
and throat are open for vowel sounds.
Consonant sounds have
some kind of closure or constriction.
For example, in the consonant sounds
that we've learned thus far,
P,B, and M in Day 1 and 2,
the lips close and then open.
And for the F and V sounds
in Day 3 and 4, there was a
constriction between the teeth and the lip.
between the teeth and the lip.
The air has to pass over that constriction
[prolonged F sound].
And even the hard C or the K sound,
which is invisible,
has the constriction at the back of the throat.
Try saying a K sound
and have that constriction
at the back of your throat. [K]
So vowels are open,
and consonants have some kind of closure or constriction.
Another thing to know about vowels is
that they're categorized as
being short, long or diphthongs.
Short vowels are marked by a breve,
which is a smiley above the vowel.
They are short because they're said quickly,
and they're quite difficult to see at times.
Long vowels are marked by a straight line
over the vowel,
called a macron.
Long vowels are said
the same way we pronounce them
in the alphabet A, E, I, O, and U.
Long vowels are easier to prolong.
Diphthongs are a union of two vowels.
An example is the oi sound in boy.
Boy definition, uh,
by definition,
diphthongs are long vowels
because they contain two vowel sounds.
Let's make sure you know
the difference between
short and long vowels.
For the vowel A,
A is long in apron and whale.
A is short in black and apple.
As we go through these,
try to notice that
the short vowels are quite difficult to see
because they're passing by so quickly.
For the vowel E,
E is long in easel and key.
E is short in egg and effort.
For the vowel I,
it's long in ice and bright.
It's short in itch and six.
For the vowel O,
O is long in overalls and boat.
O is short in octopus and fox.
For the vowel U,
it's long in uniform and blue.
U is short in umbrella and fun.
Let's practice.
I'll say a word and you tell me
if it's short or long.
I'm also going to use this opportunity
to review invisible sounds
and introduce a new one.
Are you ready?
Short or long?
Ape
Ape is long
The next one is cap.
Cap is short.
Cap looks like app,
because the hard C sound
is invisible at the beginning of the word.
Combine that with a short vowel,
and cap is pretty hard to speech read!
Short or long?
Eggnog
Both vowels in eggnog are short.
They also have an invisible G
at the end of egg and nog,
so a short vowel plus invisible sounds
makes another word
that's difficult to speech read!
Short or long?
Night
The I sound in night is long.
Short or long?
YouTube
Both “U”s in YouTube
are long.
The last short or long example is a phrase:
the red fox
This phrase is full of short vowels.
It also has a new invisible sound, the X.
The X sound is actually made of two sounds,
the K and the S.
Try it now.
Say the letter X to yourself
and separate out the K and the S.
[X]
The S is visible,
the K is not visible.
So you don't see the X,
you see the S.
[Fox]
So make sure you add X=K + S
to your list of invisible sounds.
Because the short vowels
are so difficult to recognize and see,
we're actually not going
to study them any further.
If you have difficulty with a word or a phrase
it's likely going to be
when there's short vowels in it.
There's not much you can do about it
except be aware of it.
That's why we did the long and short practice.
And now for a communication tip.
If you have difficulty hearing and seeing someone
even after they repeated it,
you could ask them to rephrase,
instead of saying “What?” a second time.
Potentially the original word or phrase
had short vowels in it and maybe some invisible sounds.
And then when they rephrase it, it might
have long vowels and be easier for you to see.
I'll give you an example.
Watch me as I say a sentence silently.
Are you ready?
Pardon?
Hmm, I still didn't get it.
Can you say it a different way?
Absolutely, I'd be happy to.
The original sentence was:
I like your picture of a red fox.
And the rephrase was,
I love your photo of the red fox,
so I changed “like” to “love,”
and emphasized it just a bit more.
And then I changed
the word picture,
which has two vowels that are short,
to photo,
which has two vowels that are long.
Plus you had an actual photo
for context.
Did that make it easier for you?
I'll do it again
Here's another example of rephrasing.
Instead of saying,
Seconds on the cheddar, if possible
I could rephrase to:
More cheese, please!
Those long vowels are easier
to prolong and emphasize.
I have a question for you.
How would you ask someone to rephrase?
We all have different ways of saying things,
so what works for me might not work for you.
I do think your delivery is important:
the way you say something
and the words that you use
when you're asking someone
to do something for you.
Give it some thought,
and let me know in the comments.
Okay that's it for today!
Tomorrow, we'll get practice
lip reading long vowels.
In the meantime,
please like my video,
subscribe to my channel,
and especially share this with others.
Sometimes it takes a little bit of effort
to sign into Google
in order to be able to like and subscribe,
and I appreciate that effort.
That's what makes free content
go around on YouTube.
Literally.
The more people who like
and subscribe and engage by commenting,
the more people who will see this
video in the future.
So thank you, thank you,
Thanks for your help.
Bye!